# BENCIPOLLINI

DATA SCIENCE LEADER

# CONTACT

- (619) 752-0620
- ben.cipollini@gmail.com
- Hayward, CA, USA
- https://www.linkedin.com/s ocial-sector-data-insights

# **EDUCATION**

## Ph.D in Cognitive Science

UC San Diego La Jolla, CA | 2014

### B.S. in Computer Science

Lehigh University
Bethlehem, PA | 1998

## SKILLS

- Building and managing
   high-performing data teams
- Measuring and accelerating growth via alignment on goals.
- Product & business strategy, with strong data comms skills.
- Public thought leadership via content creation, webinars, etc.
- End-to-end tech leadership, from data infrastructure to insights, front-of-business to product.

# INTERESTS

Physics, Photography, Hiking, Motorcycling, Entrepreneurship

## PROFILE

I'm a tech-savvy data science leader with expertise in social sector datasets and social media products. I've built and driven highly successful, diverse data teams at both startups and large tech companies. I've led research teams to generate and publish industry-leading data insights that lead to measurable business impact.

# EXPERIENCE

#### PRODUCT DATA SCIENCE MANAGER

META | MENLO PARK, CA | 2019 - PRESENT

Lead Social Impact product organization (managing 6 DS, lead 24 analytics) to support 1 product with \$1.5B annual turnover and launch 3 new 0-to-1 products.

- Increased total fundraised by over 50%, incl. launch of Instagram fundraising.
- Led strategic pivot to serve nonprofits, increasing fundraising TAM by 20x.
- Launched new products for giving of goods and time, increasing TAM by >2x.

## DIRECTOR OF DATA SCIENCE

CLASSY.ORG | SAN DIEGO, CA | 2015 - 2019

Designed, built, and owned Classy's analytics infrastructure and team. Owned setting company KPIs, Classy's annual <u>State of Modern Philanthropy report</u>.

- Built Classy's data infra (data warehouse (AWS), ETL (python), BI (Looker), analysis (python/R)), enabling sales, product and fundraising metrics visibility.
- Led company goaling; led definition of product and finance KPIs; created dashboard for first C-level visibility. Presented quarterly to company leadership.
- Pitched & published Classy's first two State of Modern Philanthropy annual reports, driving industry awareness and generating >1K new sales leads.

#### DATA SCIENCE LEAD

GIVINGTUESDAY.ORG | REMOTE | 2018 - 2021

Led team of 4 on definition and execution across data engineering, analytics, and research. Owned end-to-end definition & delivery of data deliverables.

- Led cross-org effort to revamp the top nonprofit fundraising benchmark.
- Led design & execution of automated data ingestion across 40+ providers & >\$3B.
- Led whitepaper publications, including <u>2020 Fundraising Look-Back</u>, first-of-kind <u>Volunteer report</u>, and <u>early-pandemic fundraising report</u>.